<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc>
<s>A broad curve that ends with a little curl, so that I <m>face the exact <l>location of my entrance</l></m>.</s>
<s>I <m>appear at</m> the <l>edge of the stage</l> as the last few audience members take their seats.</s>
<s>My behavior is matter-of-fact.</s>
<s>I have a lot of choices to make in advance of my entrance.</s>
<s>I decide on my <l>entrance site</l> and the direction I will travel in relation to the <l>audience</l>, plus <l>where that path will end</l>.</s>
<s>Then the light fades.</s>
<s>The moment the light returns I <m>step onto</m> the <l>stage</l>, <m>walking</m> in a stride and style not mine, as foreign as a foreign accent, recognizable but odd.</s>
<s>The path is a singular broad curve that ends in a slightly accelerated little curl, leaving me <m>facing the</m> <l>portal</l> through which I stepped onto the <l>stage</l>.</s>
<s>Nothing about my performance ends at the <l>end of the curl</l>.</s>
<s>I am <m>held by</m> an imagined cord linking me to the <l>portal</l>.</s>
<s>I attend to the exactness of the single <l>broad curve</l> so that when I <m>face my</m> <l>entrance site</l> it is as f I complete the stringing of an archer's bow.</s>
<s>I deliberately create this space within a space, separating me from the <l>audience</l>.</s>
<s>An ancient voice quietly advises me to remember the <l>audience</l> as well as the space beyond my tightly contained space.</s>
<s>The ancient voice is me from 10000 years ago or from 10000 years in the future – a compassionate voice bringing the experience from the past or from the future into the present.</s>
<s>In response to the guidance received, I select the right moment to break the string and notice at once how the inclusion of the <l>theater</l> and my <l>audience</l> enlarges my dancing.</s>
<s>It is like a real opening, and I begin again.</s>
<s>My choice to perform this material requires catastrophic acts of perception.</s>
<s>I associate catastrophic with images of great loss.</s>
<s>The magnitude and reoccurrence of choreographed behavior that I need to first recognize and then dis-attach from, again and again, is a personal lass of tremendous proportion.</s>
<s>My <m>body is still</m> while joy and sorrow wash across my face like a stream of instances.</s>
<s>A full smile or frown is never fulfilled.</s>
<s>When not streaming, my face may briefly <m>return to normalcy</m>, or it may <m>sustain</m> a single reflection of joy/sorrow for longer moments.</s>
<s>I am not limited to my personal experience of joy and sorrow.</s>
<s>It is a relief to know that it is in and about the <l>audience</l>, this <l>theater</l>, and the <l>world</l> beyond its <l>doors</l>.</s>
<s>As I perform, I try to remove my tendency to embody the images I use to describe the movement material.</s>
<s>I sing a wordless song that arises from and combines joy and sorrow into a single melody that resonates through my stilled bones.</s>
<s>Barely suppressing a sense of personal history, my face reflects the transience of joy and sorrow.</s>
<s>I hear the song as my voice leaves my <l>body</l>.</s>
<s>I am intentionally unguarded because I rarely allow myself to partake in unprotected experiences.</s>
<s>I am not translating the written language into movement, i.e., joy and sorrow.</s>
<s>I actually aspire toward a bodily speechlessness by noticing my visual field, which includes what I can and cannot see, as well as minute associative instances that rise spontaneously.</s>
<s>I understand that joy and sorrow are always present.</s>
<s>I do not have to instigate them.</s>
<s>The song's duration is determined by how much time is required for it to impress itself on my body and the audience's memory.</s>
<s>The phrasing of the song can expand and contract.</s>
<s>Singing a song of joy and sorrow is a challengingly simple way for me to engage my perception of space and time.</s>
<s>I <m>attach rhythmic movement</m> to the song, my dancing obviously influenced by my singing.</s>
<s>I establish this continuity of relationship before using it to <m>navigate a slightly complex path</m> to the <l>edge of the stage</l>.</s>
<s>I strongly maintain the role of the choreographer, overseeing the particularity of the path I travel and making spatial choices without becoming too artistic.</s>
<s>Partway, my audible singing disappears, yet the dancing adheres to its reliance on the now unheard rhythm of the song.</s>
<s>And finally my dance shifts outside of the prevailing memory of the song, and I <m>move across</m> <l>stage</l> in a straight line while erasing my destination.</s>
<s>While dancing I make an effort not to hesitate.</s>
<s>Learned behavior suggests I <m>slow down</m> or listen more in order to get things right.</s>
<s>That is a belief that limits my dance.</s>
<s>At the <l>edge of the stage</l>, with a 1-minute allotment to <m>turn in place a single time</m> without moving slowly or continuously, I perform the joy and sorrow in restraint and sing a fraction of the joy/sorrow song on two or three occasions during the turn.</s>
<s>My <m>head is free to look down or away or to turn</m>.</s>
<s>It is not fixed.</s>
<s>If the sparsely singing turn is like a lock unlocking, then WORK is my deliverance into space after one minute.</s>
<s>I <m>accept any movement that arises spontaneously</m> and call it WORK.</s>
<s>WORK is a variation on a 2-part, 2-second spontaneous movement used to <m>cross</m> the <l>stage</l> one time.</s>
<s>Because of the banality of the choreography, WORK is also how I manage the choreographic tools I need to maintain both my interest and that of the audience.</s>
<s>Those tools are the perception of my movement as music, my perception of space, the use of stillness and duration, and the perception of joy and sorrow to deepen my practice of performance.</s>
<s>During this movement it is helpful to enlarge my perception of space beyond the <l>theater</l>.</s>
<s>There is no repetition in live performance.</s>
<s>WORK comes easily.</s>
<s>Maybe it is because of what is required to survive as a dancer in contemporary western culture.</s>
<s>It can be difficult to dis-attach from the habitual physical response to what "work" looks like, i.e., striving, reaching, pushing, dragging, busying, flailing, hauling.</s>
<s>I <m>neither hurry nor linger</m>.</s>
<s>COMPLEXITY arises.</s>
<s>I play havoc with how I perceive time and how I perceive space rather than creating complex body movement.</s>
<s>CLEARING THE DANCE OF COMPLEXITY is as abstruse, yet here I am, the two occurrences weaving back and forth several times.</s>
<s>The duration of the two directions is choreographically challenging.</s>
<s>The movement is not difficult just because I use the words COMPLEXITY, havoc, abstruse, choreographically challenging.</s>
<s>And CLEARING THE DANCE OF COMPLEXITY does not necessarily require flowing movement.</s>
<s>If I can manage my perception of time and space to inform my body, then I do not have to think about what movement to do next.</s>
<s>What I mean by my perception of time is that it is passing.</s>
<s>And what I mean by my perception of space is that I include it in my dancing so that I am not seduced by the intelligence, past experiences, patterns, limitations, and/or sensuality of my moving body.</s>
<s>I perform market, a contemporary market, A MALL.</s>
<s>Without creating A MALL I notice it wherever I am.</s>
<s>I attend to my perception of space and time in order to distract myself from predetermining the outcome of this choreographic direction.</s>
<s>It is an effort to refrain from creating a literal mall.</s>
<s>Instead, copious instances of A MALL appear and disappear as I dance.</s>
<s>A single OBJECT reveals itself in A MALL.</s>
<s>I perform several views of OBJECT for the benefit of the audience.</s>
<s>A MALL and OBJECT alternate their appearances.</s>
<s>As in COMPLEXITY and freedom from it, the duration of the two directions is challenging.</s>
<s>I do not create OBJECT.</s>
<s>I learn its attributes from my body and actually take pleasure in identifying the object for myself in each performance.</s>
<s>I remember to notice that my whole body is producing unimaginable instances of specificity.</s>
<s>I <m>start spinning</m>, not literally but as a part of an onstage counterclockwise spinning vortex that only I perceive.</s>
<s>I am a speck, a dot, a flake, endlessly spiraling toward <l>center stage</l>, and absolutely no one can possibly identify me as such.</s>
<s>The movement may change, but the choreography itself does not change.</s>
<s>At <l>center stage</l> I <m>reverse direction</m> and <m>turn in place</m> while <m>lifting my arms</m> incrementally, <m>building up my torso</m>, to signify the construction and architecture of A HOLY SITE.</s>
<s>At the same time my shoes lightly <m>tap the</m> <l>floor</l> under me as if to imply the sporadic thwacks of a hammer, striking in the distance.</s>
<s>I am A HOLY SITE and to perform as such requires the catastrophic loss of how I otherwise perceive myself.</s>
<s>A HOLY SITE is completed the moment my <m>hands or fingers touch overhead</m>.</s>
<s>I <m>open my mouth</m> and hear A HOLY SONG rise up out of me.</s>
<s>I am not a singer and cannot carry a tune.</s>
<s>Nevertheless I call what I hear A HOLY SONG and notice the feedback from my whole body as it yields to that direction.</s>
<s>Unable to sustain itself, A HOLY SITE collapses.</s>
<s>My <m>hands, still touching, drop</m> before my eyes.</s>
<s>I contemplate the symbolism of the gestural demise.</s>
<s>Then my <m>arms, in relation to my torso, shape a</m> really primitive resemblance to A TOTEM POLE.</s>
<s>Resourcing whatever bits of prior exposure to an American Indian chant, I reproduce it as best as I can while <m>rhythmlessly bouncing</m> to beating drums that only I can hear.</s>
<s>A TOTEM POLE collapses, and the chant dissipates under the weight of the gestural obsolescence.</s>
<s>Back and forth, A HOLY SITE and A HOLY SONG and A TOTEM POLE with an American Indian chant collapse.</s>
<s>And I rebuild, using the sound of my tapping feet to symbolize a hammer.</s>
<s>I travel in fading light.</s>
<s>Light returns and I am <m>tiptoeing</m>, not wanting to disrupt the space already created – a task I hold in high regard.</s>
<s>I experience space parting, with little to no disturbance, hoping that the audience will see this too, before arriving somewhere that is <l>not center stage</l>.</s>
<s>My actions are obvious.</s>
<s>When I imagine the <l>stage</l> is still, the <m>fingertips of each hand instantaneously clutch and attach to two different points on my body</m>, creating a sculptural resemblance to a totem pole, which I may be the only person in the world to realize.</s>
<s>An intermittent return to the American Indian prayer/chant arises, punctuated by beating drums that only I can hear.</s>
<s>My basically <m>upright torso bounces rhythmlessly</m> with the supposed drums.</s>
<s>I alternate the prayer/chant with silences of different duration and incrementally <m>lower each arm</m> without anyone noticing.., while continuing to maintain the movement of the totem pole/drum beat.</s>
<s>In this manner I keep myself alert.</s>
<s>Just before my right arm relaxes completely, I <m>lift and point my right index finger in the air</m> and, speaking in a Southern accent, say, "Strictly speaking I believe I have never been anywhere." [Beckett]2 </s>
<s>With my <m>finger still in the air</m>, I leave time for the Beckett quote to sink in.</s>
<s>The quote's impact on my body is mind-boggling.</s>
<s>My <m>right index finger lowers</m> as I sing the tune "Oh, they don't wear pants in the sunny side of France. But they do wear grass, to cover up their ass." </s>
<s>My perception of joy and sorrow guides the singing.</s>
<s>The lifetime of the song is how long it takes for my finger to lower.</s>
<s>My standard for "lower" is my own.</s>
<s>It is possible to <m>travel</m> and <m>add movement</m> within the finger/song dance cycle.</s>
<s>I sing, and <m>my finger, corresponding to the song's phrasing, moves in a downward direction</m>, or I am silent as the finger moves downward, or the duration of my singing and silences are juxtaposed as the <m>finger lowers</m>.</s>
<s>At the end of the finger path I perform a generous instant of A 5000-YEAR-OLD MARKETPLACE – primarily still.</s>
<s>The finger/song dance is repeated the instant I <m>return my finger above my head</m> in order to lower it for a second time.</s>
<s>My finger can be a trap.</s>
<s>I do not fixate on it – deliberately hiding its function in determining my movement.</s>
<s>I am unquantifiable instances of A 5000-YEAR-OLD MARKETPLACE before sunrise, while it is still dark and quiet.</s>
<s>I depend on the image at first, and then I get rid of it.</s>
<s>This is not a narrative.</s>
<s>Maybe a wind moves the air around a makeshift pole, flap, cover, knot, uneven surface.</s>
<s>My <m>hand occasionally thrums my body</m> for sound, or make short intermittent sounds that are barely audible.</s>
<s>It is an effort to refrain from creating a marketplace.</s>
<s>Instead, copious instances of predawn marketplace live and die spontaneously.</s>
<s>It is all I need.</s>
<s>It is the same for a single item, like a particular utensil, crafted tool, or ornament – an UNTRADITIONAL OBJECT in a 5000-year-old marketplace.</s>
<s>There is no name for the item, fortunately.</s>
<s>I depend on the poetry, but I get rid of any imagery as soon as I remember to notice that my whole body is producing unimaginable instances of specificity.</s>
<s>I learn the object's attributes from my body and actually take pleasure in identifying it for myself in each performance.</s>
<s>I provide several views of an UNTRADITIONAL OBJECT for the audience.</s>
<s>The marketplace, with its goods, like a 40-camel caravan embarks on a clunkety journey through a limitless landscape.</s>
<s>Think sand, then forget sand.</s>
<s>I travel several directions at once, <m>proceeding along a single path</m>.</s>
<s>The movements of my hips, legs, knees, and feet symbolize obstacles along the way.</s>
<s>The movement is not difficult just because I use the word "obstacles." </s>
<s>I am not translating the written language into movement, i.e., marketplace, goods, caravan, empty landscape, obstacles.</s>
<s>I actually aspire toward a bodily speechlessness so that I can notice and appreciate the abundance of materiality that can surface momentarily.</s>
<s>I perform counterintuitive travel somewhere at the <l>edge of the space</l>.</s>
<s>A cranky voice provides continuous accompaniment.</s>
<s>The term "counterintuitive travel" is not any different than "clunkety journey," in that it is what it is – another way.</s>
<s>Counterintuitive reflects possibility, not intention, psychology, or effort.</s>
<s>I do not become cranky.</s>
<s>Cranky describes my voice.</s>
<s>I MEND the field.</s>
<s>Accepting any movement, I call it MEND.</s>
<s>At the same time it is an effort <m>not to automatically produce comforting arm or hand movements</m> or behave like a mother hen.</s>
<s>I build a road with my feet used to smooth and design its surface.</s>
<s>My work is clear and evident, without rest.</s>
<s>I make a rhythmic sound, like an engine, to create a counterpart to the work of building the road.</s>
<s>My <m>arms, held out</m> from my body, symbolize the shape of the engine.</s>
<s>I strongly maintain the role of the choreographer, overseeing the design element of the road.</s>
<s>I think of the road's surface as a mosaic, without getting too artistic.</s>
<s>I <m>turn and turn and turn</m>, as many times as I remain interested in turning on this big new road, bringing separate parts together in a whirling whole that becomes A HOLY SITE at the <l>center of the stage</l>.</s>
<s>The turning is happening in my perception of the <l>whole stage</l>, and my body is just a part of it.</s>
<s>My <m>arms are above my head</m>, and they function as the architecture of the temple, shrine, church, mosque, etc.</s>
<s>My hands, like antenna, draw A HOLY SONG down through A HOLY SITE and out through my mouth.</s>
<s>It does not have to be anything other than holy – holy being different for everyone.</s>
<s>I close my lips, and the song <m>enters my mouth</m>.</s>
<s>My <m>cheeks enlarge</m>, but the song does not escape.</s>
<s>I let go of the now compressed sound, in two increments that correspond to the <m>collapse of my arms</m>, poised like a mound of rubble in front of me.</s>
<s><m>Holding my body still</m>, I <m>step toward</m> the <l>audience</l> to offer them several views of the former holy site.</s>
<s>To return to <l>center stage</l> I rebuild the road, using my feet and voice as I did while building the road the first time.</s>
<s>At <l>center stage</l>, my <m>arms again lift above my head</m> to symbolize the architecture of A HOLY SITE, and A HOLY SONG returns.</s>
<s>A second abrupt fall with its single compressed sound destroys the holy site, turning it back into rubble.</s>
<s>My ancient self's voice guides me back to a standing position.</s>
<s>Everything seems in order.</s>
<s>I am <m>standing straight</m>, except that I am <m>facing away</m> from the <l>audience</l>.</s>
<s>The final encouragement I receive from my ancient self has me <m>turn to face the</m> <l>audience</l> once more.</s>
<s>Pause.</s>
<s>When my face begins streaming with joy and sorrow, that is the end.</s>
</doc>